Hi, this is Dr. Flaum, and
today's lecture will be on
deductions to
articulatory or ART and
myofascial release
MFR techniques.
Our learning
objectives will be to
understand the
principles of ART and
myofascial release
and applications,
the indications and
contraindications of both,
understand the basic
technique principles of
both, and to understand
the principles of regional
versus segmental versus
peripheral ART and
their applications and
to understand the models
of myofascial release
and their applications.
Articulatory method, or
ART, is a direct joint
-focused group of techniques
which use low-velocity,
high-amplitude, LVAH
movements. In performing
treatment, the physician
gently carries the body
region being treated
through the restrictive
barrier. This may be done
as a single movement or
repetitively. Repetitive
techniques are often referred
to as springing. Many
articulatory techniques
use long-level forces to
achieve their effects.
Indications would be
restrictive motion in the
presence of articulatory
or myofascial somatic
dysfunction, especially in
the frail or elderly, and
circulatory and lymphatic
ingestion. Conscious
indications would be
acute, moderate to severe
strain or sprain, fracture,
dislocation, or joint
instability in the area
affected by the treatment,
acute inflammatory
joint disease in the
area affected by the
treatment, metastasis
in the area affected
by the treatment,
neurologic
entrapment syndromes,
serious vascular
compromised infection, for
example, cellulitis,
abscess, septic arthritis,
osteomyelitis, or
bleeding disorders.
Basic technique principles
for ART would be
that the patient should
be comfortable and able
to relax. The physician
should also be in a
position of comfort to
minimize energy expenditure
and to make use of body
weight and leverage
rather than having to
exert muscular force.
The physician moves the
affected joint of body
parts through its range
of motion until the
restrictive barrier is
engaged. A gentle but firm
force is applied carrying
the body region a short
distance through the
restrictive barrier. The
distance is limited by
the tissues being treated
and the patient's tolerance
to pain or fatigue.
This force is typically
applied rhythmically,
consisting of one or
two seconds of stretch,
followed by a similar time
frame for releasing the
stretch. The joint is
permitted to return to
a point just short of
its restrictive barrier.
As the patient responds to
the technique, the restrictive
barrier will shift position
within the physiologic
range of motion. For
each cycle of the applied
technique, re-engagement of
the restricted barrier and
carry the affected body region
a short distance farther
through the new barrier
to a normal motion. The
applied forces should be
comfortable to the patient. Some
patients experience discomfort,
but it is recognized
by the patient as a good
and necessary discomfort.
The technique is continued
until the location
of the restricted barrier
reaches a plateau.
that is, no further
increase in range of motion
can be achieved by a
continuing technique or
until full physiologic
range of motion has been
restored to the joint
or joints being treated.
At no time is the
anatomic barrier
to the joint motion exceeded.
And as with all OMM techniques,
reassessment should
be done at the end.
There are three
types of articulatory
techniques. One
would be regional,
and this may be applied
to the entire region
of the spine to improve
regional range of motion
when the restriction
to motion is perceived
by the physician to have
an articular component
to it, for example,
cervical side bending.
Second technique or type
would be segmental, where
it is applied segmentally
to motion restrictions
that are perceived to
be a particular nature
in their vertebral
column. Example would
be segmental synodic
dysfunction at C4.
Third type would be peripheral,
and this is especially
useful in treating motion
or restriction of motion
of the peripheral limb
joints, for example,
radiocarpal joint restriction.
Key concepts of ART is
that it involves gentle or
impedive motions through
the restricted barrier,
or one of the most
versatile treatment forms
available since the physician
can use a wide range
of force levels and adapt
them to a variety of
patient body types and
locations of dysfunction,
and many techniques use long
-level forces in
achieving effects.
myofascial release is a system
of diagnosis and treatment
first described by at still
as early students which
engages continual palpatory
feedback to achieve
release of myofascial tissues
it can be applied as a direct
or indirect technique
and a direct technique to
restrict the barriers identified
in the myofascial tissues
and engage with a loaded
constant directional force
until the tissue releases
and motions restored in an
indirect technique, the
tissue position of ease is
identified and engaged with
directed pressure. This guides
the tissue along the line
at least resistance until
freedom of all tissues
is achieved. A combined
procedure, whereby the physician
hands engage both a point
of barrier and a point of
ease simultaneously, allows
the myofascial release to
occur through the application
of both direct and indirect
methods interactively.
Activating portions used
in myofascial release could
be an inherent or intrinsic
force, which uses the
body's natural tendency to
seek homeostasis. Inherent
forces is the rhythmic
activity in all tissues, which
works to improve the
hydrodynamic and bioenergetic
factors around restricted
tissues and articulations.
Another one would be the
respiratory force, which
is a cooperation or assist
and may be used in four
ways. While using a direct
or indirect technique,
full cycle respiratory
effort is applied as a
fascial and or articulatory
activating force. Once
positioned, the particular
phase of respiration
enhances the position of
the area of being treated.
Breath holding for the
maximum time the patient
can tolerate causes
air hunger and triggers
a generalized relaxation
of soft tissues.
Coughing or sniffing on
command produces a respiratory
impulse to assist in the
release of restrictions.
Patient cooperation. Patient
is requested to move in
specific directions in
various planes of articulation
to aid in immobilizing
an error of restriction.
Physician guided force.
After engaging a barrier or
point of ease, the physician
sequentially guides the
tissue adjoint through
various positions following a
shifting pattern of ease
motion until the path of
dysfunction is retraced and
released. Stringing or vibration.
placing the hand or
percussion hammer on a
dysfunction and applying
variable degrees of pressure and
the frequency of force,
causing the springing of
vibration structure, activates
release of the tissues.
These go through the
various models of myofascial
release, which include
the biomechanical model,
the fascial continuum of
the big bandage model,
and the bioenergetic
model, and goes through the
various techniques, tissue
focus, and emphasis.
myofascial release
indications to treat somatic
dysfunction involving
myofascial tissues or
other connective tissues
to alleviate the visceral
and somatic components
of somatic dysfunction
in the connective tissues
of the body with a
focus on fascia muscles
and related structures
neuroreflexive circulatory
lymphatic respiratory
bioenergetic systemic
holographic and
homeostatic and to address
structural imbalances
and somatic dysfunctions
indicative of and pursuant
to changes in homeostasis
and systemic disease to
aid in the normalization
function of both systems.
Myofascial release
techniques address
max function by
normalizing motion,
relieving edema, reestablishing
symmetry, relieving
pain, aiding circulatory
and lymphatic function,
normalizing
neuroflexive activity,
supporting visceral function,
restoring bioenergetic
balance and supporting
homeostatic function.
Conscientications.
Cautions and relative
conscientications for
local application would be
fractures of the wounds,
soft tissues, or bony
infections, abscesses, DVT,
coagulopathy, neoplasm,
directly over the
site of a recent
operation, and aortic aneurysm.
General considerations
and rules.
The physician palpates
the patient using layer-by
-layer palpatory principles
and adjust enough pressure to
capture the skin as it
continues ****** structures.
This is one level of pressure
less than that of soft tissue.
Any movement of the
hand on skin should
cause the skin to move
along with the hand
without sliding the
hand over the skin.
The physician gently
moves the palpating hand
or hands in a linear
direction of choice,
hands of the clock, moving
through X and Y axis.
disease. The z-axis
has already been gauged
by the layer of palpatory
pressure into the
body, gaining access to
the superficial fascia.
Symmetry versus asymmetry
of tissue compliance
is noted in the linear
directions tested.
The physician may add
a variety of directions
of motion, including other
linear movements in a
360-degree reference
and clockwise and
counterclockwise rotational
movement. Again, symmetry
versus asymmetry of tissue
compliance is noted.
The pressure the physician
uses to determine
compliance may be minimal
or moderate depending
on the clinical
presentation of the patient,
acute painful versus
chronic minimally
painful, and what the
physician believes
is appropriate
for the situation.
And to determine the ease
and bind barriers of the
tissue in these directions,
the physician determines
whether gentle or
moderate pressure in a
direct toward the bind or
indirect toward ease technique
is appropriate. Again,
this is determined by
the clinical presentation
and examination findings.
In general, the gentlest
method is the safest.
The physician slowly
moves the hand-controlled
myofascial tissues toward
the appropriate barrier, and
on meeting the barrier, he
or she holds the tissue at
that point without relieving
the pressure. A physician
should notice that after
approximately 20 to 30
seconds, a change of tissue
compliance occurs. This
is demonstrated by moving
the tissue through the
originally determined barrier
creep or fascial creep.
the physician follows this
change and continues to
engage the barrier until
no further evidence of
creep occurs there may
be a number of compliance
changes creep before
this phenomenon stops the
physician re-evaluates the
tissue to determine whether
the tissue's compliance
and quality have improved
this technique may be
repeated at the same area
or another and follow
visits may be prescribed for
a three-day interval or
longer depending on patient
reactivity and always,
always, always reassess.
Key concepts emphasizes
appreciation and recruitment
of the innate and inherent
motion of the myofascial
structures that identifies
patterns of motion
and ease across
proximal and distal
structures, diaphragms,
departments, etc., and
organ systems includes
myofascial release,
integrated neural
muscle skeletal release,
fascial ligamentous release,
and biological fascial
activity release.
Respiratory assistance,
falcrums, body
positions, neuroflexive
activities, oscillations,
passive progressive
motions, and menstrual
contractions may
aid in the progress
of myofascial release.
Thank you. End of lecture.